Section 6.2 reinforcement learning warning
this is meant as
a recap. If you are already familiar with
the
basics, you can skip directly to the next
section.
The section provides a succinct reminder
of several concepts
in reinforcement learning. It also
disambiguates various often conflated
terms such as rewards, values and
utilities. The section
ends with a discussion around
distinguishing the concept of
objectives that a reinforcement learning
system might pursue from
what it is being rewarded for. Primer Here
is
a definition of reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning focuses on
developing agents that can learn from
interactive experiences. RL
is based on the concept of an agent
learning
through interaction with an environment
and altering its behavior
based on the feedback it receives through
rewards after
each action. The textbook includes video
6.1 here, which
you may want to watch separately. It
covers optional
video showcasing robotic hand trained
using reinforcement learning Some
examples of real world applications of RL
robotic Systems
RL has been applied to tasks such as
controlling
physical robots in real time and enabling
them to
learn more complicated movements. RL can
enable robotic systems
to learn complex tasks and adapt to
changing environments.
RL can be applied to recommender systems
which interact
with billions of users and aim to provide
personalized
recommendations. RL algorithms can learn
to optimize the recommendation
policy based on user feedback and improve
the overall
user experience. In the early 2010s, RL
based systems
started to beat humans at a few very
simple
Atari games like Pong and Breakout. Over
the years
there have been many models that have
utilized RL
to defeat world masters in both board and
video
games. These include models like AlphaGo,
DeepMind, AlphaZero, DeepMind
2018, OpenAI 5, OpenAI 2019, Alpha Star,
DeepMind 2019,
Muzero, DeepMind 2020 and Efficient Zero
Year et al.
2021. RL is different from supervised
learning as it
begins with a high level description of
what to
do, but allows the agent to experiment and
learn
from experience. The best how? In rl, the
agent
learns through interaction with an
environment and receives feedback
in the form of rewards or punishments
based on
its actions. RL is focused on learning a
set
of rules that recommend the best action to
take
in a given state to maximize long term
rewards.
In contrast, supervised learning typically
involves learning from explicitly
provided labels or correct answers for
each input core
loop. The overall functioning of RL is
relatively straightforward.
The two main components are the agent
itself and
the environment within which the agent
lives and operates
at each time. Step 1 the agent then takes
some action a sub T a 2 the environment
state S sub t changes depending upon the
action
A, sub T3. The environment then outputs an
observation
O, sub t and a reward R, sub t.
A history is the sequence of past
observations, actions,
and rewards that have been taken up until
time.
Sub t is the sequence of AOR triples from
1 to T. The state of the world is
generally some function of the history S,
sub t
equals f of H, sub t. The world state
is the full true state of the world used
to determine how the world generates the
next observation
and reward. The agent might either get the
entire
world state as an observation a sub t, or
some partial subset. The world goes from
one state,
sub T to the next S, sub T plus
1, either based on natural environmental
dynamics or the
agent's actions. State transitions can be
both deterministic or
stochastic. This loop continues until a
terminal condition is
reached or can run indefinitely. Following
is a diagram
that succinctly captures the RL process.
At this point,
the textbook shows Figure 6.1. Policies we
define reinforcement
learning policy as follows. A policy helps
the agent
determine what action to take once it has
received
an observation. It is a function mapping
from states
to actions specifying what action to take
in each
state. Policies can be both deterministic
or stochastic. The
goal of RL is to learn a policy, often
denoted by PI, that recommends the best
action to
take at any given moment in order to
maximize
total cumulative reward over time. The
policy defines the
mapping from states to actions and guides
the agent's
decision making process. PI maps from S to
a.
A policy can be either deterministic or
stochastic. A
deterministic policy directly maps each
state's sub t to
a specific action A sub t and is usually
denoted by mu. In contrast, a stochastic
policy assigns
a probability distribution over actions
for each state. Stochastic
policies usually denoted by PI.
Deterministic policy A sub
t equals mu of SE sub t Stochastic policy
PI of a given SS equals the probability
that
A, sub t equals a given that s sub
t equals s in deep rl, policies are
function
maps that are learned during the training
process. They
depend on the set of learned parameters of
a
neural network, eg the weights and biases.
These parameters
are often denoted with subscripts on the
policy equations
using either theta or phi phi. So the
deterministic
policy over the parameters of a neural
network is
written A sub t equals mu sub theta of
S sub t and the stochastic equivalent is A
sub t is sampled from PI sub theta of
c dot given S, sub t. An optimal policy
maximizes the expected cumulative reward
over time, the agent
learns from experience and adjusts its
policy based on
the feedback it receives from the
environment in the
form of rewards or punishments. In order
to determine
whether an action is better than another,
the actions
or the state action pairs need to be
evaluated
somehow. There are two different ways to
look at
which action to take the immediate rewards
determined by
reward function and the long term
cumulative rewards determined
by the action value function. Both of
these greatly
influence the types of policies learned by
the agent
and therefore also the actions that the
agent takes.
The following section explores and
clarifies the concept of
rewards in greater depth. Reward the term
reward refers
to the following Reward refers to any
signal or
feedback mechanism used to guide the
learning process and
optimize the behavior of the model. The
reward signal
from the environment is a number that
tells the
agent how good or bad the current world
state
is. It is a way to provide an evaluation
or measure of performance for the model's
outputs or
actions. The reward can be defined based
on a
specific task or objective, such as
maximizing a score
in a game or achieving a desired outcome
in
a real world scenario. The training
process for RL
involves optimizing the model's parameters
and to maximize the
expected reward, the model learns to
generate actions or
outputs that are more likely to receive
higher rewards,
leading to improved performance over time.
Where does the
reward come from? It is generated through
a reward
function. We define reward function as
follows. A reward
function defines the goal or objective in
a reinforcement
learning problem. It maps perceived states
or state action
pairs of the environment to a single
number. We
have a function named capital R. This
function takes
its input from the Cartesian product of
the set
S and the set A, and it maps these
inputs to the set of real numbers.
Furthermore, we
define R, sub t as the output of this
function capital R. When it is given the
inputs
S sub t and A sub t. The reward
function provides immediate feedback to
the agent indicating the
goodness or badness of a particular state
or action.
It is a mathematical function that maps
the state
action pairs of an agent's environment to
a scalar
value representing the desirability of
being in that state
and taking that action. It provides a
measure of
immediate feedback to the agent indicating
how well it
is performing at each step. Reward
Functions versus Value
function the reward indicates the
immediate desirability of states
or actions, while a value function
represents the long
term desirability of states taking into
account future rewards
and states. The value is the expected
return if
you start in a state or state action pair
and then act according to a particular
policy forever
after. There are many different ways of
choosing value
functions. They can also be discounted
over time, I.e.
future rewards are worth less by some
factor. Following
is one simple formulation in is the
discounted sum
of future rewards given some policy? The
cumulative discounted
rewards are given by big R equals r sub
t plus gamma times r sub t plus 1
plus gamma squared times r sub plus 2 and
so on. This is also equal to the sum
From T equals 0 to infinity of gamma to
the power of t times a sub t and
the value of acting according to this
policy is
given by the value function phi under
policy PI
at the state S sub t equals s equals
the expected value under policy PI of the
reward
er, given that S sub t equals s Reward
Functions versus Utility Functions it is
also worth distinguishing
the concept of utility from reward and
value. A
reward function is typically used in the
context of
RL to guide the agent's learning process
and behavior.
In contrast, a utility function is more
general and
captures the agent's subjective
preferences or satisfaction, allowing for
comparisons and tradeoffs between
different world states. Utility functions
are a concept that is used more in the
field of decision theory and agent
foundations. Work.